קל"ח, Kuf Lamed Chet, 138, but we start on the bottom of,
not the bottom, we start at the top of קל"ז עמוד ב,
Kuf Lamed Zayin Amud Bet, yeah we're a little bit behind, but
thankfully as I said we will definitely catch up because the last
דף daf is a quarter of a page. So, so, we pick
up where we'll pick up again on קל"ז עמוד ב Kuf Lamed
Zayin Amud Bet where the גמרא Gemara says עולא אמר רבי אלעזר.
Ulla amar Rabbi Elazar. So it's one, two, three, four,
five, six, seven lines down, line starts with the word 'lo'. Okay,
so, so, so let's review what we have said. There was opinions
in the משנה Mishnah about what is the minimum amount of wool
that you need from the sheep to give to the כהן. kohen.
There was the opinion of דוסא בן הרכינס Dosa ben Harkinas that
said it was one and a half מנה maneh to correct, I
got my conversion tables mixed up yesterday, but a מנה maneh is
25 סלע, sela, which is 100 דינר. dinar. So anyway,
the first opinion was one and a half מנה maneh and we
decided a מנה maneh was about a pound, so keep that in
mind. Anyway, one and a half מנה maneh per sheep. Then the
חכמים Hachamim said no, כל שהוא, kol shehu, but the גמרא Gemara
doesn't first accept the כל שהוא kol shehu literally means כל שהוא.
kol shehu. So there are a couple of opinions. One is one
and a half מנה maneh out of all five of the sheep,
so again about one and a half pounds, but then you had
interesting figures which were a function of how much you would wind
up giving the כהן. kohen. So one position was that of שמואל
Shmuel who assumed that the minimum unit here is a סלע, sela,
you have to give a סלע's sela weight to a כהן. kohen.
Again there's 25 סלע sela to a מנה, maneh, so it's 4%
of a pound, and so שמואל Shmuel said if you have to
give a סלע sela to the כהן kohen and you have to
give a 60th of the wool to the כהן, kohen, so working
backwards, therefore what's the minimum amount of wool you need? 60 סלע
sela as opposed to before that was, we'll see in a minute,
as opposed to before which was one and a half מנה maneh
was 37 and a half. And then the other opinion said no,
no, no, it's not about a percentage, it's about an absolute amount.
The משנה Mishnah if you remember said you give five סלע sela
worth to a כהן. kohen. So if you give five סלע sela
to a כהן, kohen, you have to start with a little bit
more, so therefore six, six is the minimum amount of wool, but
then you give an absolute minimum amount not a percentage, you give
five. And now the last, now we pick up with עולא אמר
רבי אלעזר, Ulla amar Rabbi Elazar, עולא Ulla says, רבי אלעזר כל
שהוא שנינו. Rabbi Elazar kol shehu shaninu. When רבי אלעזר, Rabbi Elazar,
no did I say it right the first time? I said it
right the first time. עולא אמר רבי אלעזר כל שהוא שנינו. Ulla
amar Rabbi Elazar kol shehu shaninu. Yes, the משנה Mishnah says any
amount, any amount literally means any amount. Don't tell me six, don't
tell me 60, any amount. It's not. Now let's go back and
look at the משנה. Mishnah. וכמה נותן לו, Vekama noten lo, how
much do you give him? It says the end of the משנה,
Mishnah, not how much wool do you need, but how much do
you give the משנה? Mishnah? משקל חמש סלעים ביהודה שהן עשר סלעים
בגליל. Mishkal hamesh sela'im biYehuda shehen eser sela'im baGalil. Ten סלע sela
in יהודה Yehuda which is ten סלע sela in גליל, Galil, the
סלע sela in יהודה Yehuda were obviously bigger or heavier.
So
בשלמא לרב ורבי יוחנן ניחא. Bishlama leRav v'Rabbi Yochanan niha. According to
רב Rav and רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan it makes sense because רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan explicitly said you give a minimum amount in absolute
terms, you give five סלע, sela, and רב Rav didn't say how
much you give the minimum, he just said you need a מנה
maneh and a half to begin with. So they could both work
with the משנה Mishnah that says you give a minimum of five
סלע. sela.
אלא לשמואל ורבי אלעזר קשיא. Ela Shmuel v'Rabbi Elazar kashya. But we
got a problem. שמואל Shmuel says you give a 60th and you
could give as little as a סלע, sela, that's not the משנה,
Mishnah, the משנה Mishnah says five סלע. sela. And רבי אלעזר, Rabbi
Elazar, right, עולא Ulla in the name of רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar
says you can literally start with a כל שהוא. kol shehu. If
you start with a כל שהוא, kol shehu, you ain't giving five
סלע. sela. So we've got a problem. Our משנה Mishnah speaks about
an absolute minimum amount that you give in absolute terms, five סלע,
sela, and that does not work out according to the position of
רב Rav who says one סלע sela as a minimum and it
doesn't work out according to the position of רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar
who says you can start with a trivial amount so you're never
going to give five סלע. sela. How do you deal with it?
So of course one answer would be that you have two possible
minimums, the minimum either you can give five סלע sela as a
minimum or 1/60th, whichever is I guess less. Right, that way you
could manage both positions.
But the גמרא Gemara is not happy with that, so doesn't suggest
that at least. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. So
the גמרא Gemara says לטעמיך, leta'ameich, says the גמרא Gemara back according
to you, ולרב מי ניחא, uleRav mi niha, does it really work?
Did I skip a line? One minute. בשלמא לרב ורבי יוחנן ניחא
לשמואל ורבי אלעזר קשיא. Bishlama leRav v'Rabbi Yochanan niha leShmuel v'Rabbi Elazar
kashya. ולרב מי ניחא? uleRav mi niha?
Does it really work according to רב? Rav? רב Rav was the
one who said one and a half מנה, maneh, so does that
really make sense? Why not? והרב ושמואל דאמרי תרווייהו ראשית הגז בשישים.
VehaRav uShmuel de'amri tarvaihu reishit hagez beshishim.
רב Rav himself said in another context he agreed to this idea
of 1/60th. So we still have the problem. The משנה Mishnah says
five סלע, sela, an absolute measure as a minimum. רב Rav says
you start with one and a half מנה maneh which is again
37 and a half סלע, sela, but in another place he said
1/60th. Well 1/60th of 37 and a half is going to be
even less, about a half a סלע. sela. Okay, so we've got
these problems. The basic problem here is is that we have two
different measures of what the minimum is. Our משנה's Mishnah measure is
in absolute terms, five סלע, sela, and then we have these... other
measures which are in proportional terms, one-sixtieth. So, obviously, they're not going
to come to the same number, especially if the minimum amount of
wool you start with is going to be is going to produce
less than five סלע sela when you do one-sixtieth. So we've got
that problem. We have a position that says you can give one
סלע, sela, we have a position that says you can start with
a כל שהוא kol shehu so obviously you're giving a trivial amount.
And we have רב Rav who says you start with thirty-seven and
a half but he says in another context a sixtieth is okay.
That also gives you less than that gives you less than a
סלע. sela. How do all of those end numbers work with the
משנה Mishnah that says a minimum of five סלע? sela? So now
again, you could have said two different ways of getting to a
minimum and either one can work. But the גמרא Gemara is not
going to say that. So let's see what גמרא Gemara says. איתמר
עלה דהיא דרב ושמואל itmar ala dehi deRav uShmuel
one minute. It was said to qualify or to interpret the position
of רב Rav and שמואל, Shmuel, איתמר עלה דהיא itmar ala dehi
excuse me, רב ושמואל דאמרי תרווייהו Rav uShmuel d'amri tuvaihu that רב
Rav and שמואל Shmuel both say בישראל שיש לו גיזין הרבה עסקינן
b'Yisrael sheyesh lo gizzin harbeh askinan ומבקש ליתן לכהן umivakesh liten lekohen
ואמרינן ליה כל חד וחד לא תבצר ליה מחמישה סלעין. v'amrinan leh
kol chad v'chad lo tivtzar leh mechamesha sela'in.
They say no,
no, no, you don't understand the משנה. Mishnah. When the משנה Mishnah
says five סלע sela as a minimum, it does not mean as
a minimum if of the smallest amount that you need to give.
What it means is is that if you are apportioning out a
lot of ראשית הגז, reshit hagez, they fundamentally think the measure is
a proportion, one-sixtieth. So that can lead to a very little, as
little as a סלע, sela, could lead to a lot, could lead
to a thousand סלעין sela'in if you have a whole farm and
you've got tons of wool. So when the משנה Mishnah says five
סלע sela what it means is is that now you have a
hundred pounds of wool to give to the כהנים, kohanim, don't give
all one כהן kohen all of it. Divide it amongst different כהנים.
kohanim. And if you're dividing it amongst different כהנים, kohanim, what is
the minimum amount of a respectable thing to give to a כהן?
kohen? Five סלע. sela. So if you have more to give then
and you're dividing it, it's not appropriate to give less than five
סלע. sela. But if you don't have that amount to give, then
it's still then you give what you have. You give a proportion.
You would have thought that's פשט pshat in the משנה. Mishnah. Okay.
Alright, no, but I but look, there are different types of measures.
Logically actually you I would say the following, right, you A, you
want there to be a proportional measure, because you don't want a
guy that has millions of pounds to just give a trivial amount.
On the other hand, you also want there to be an absolute
minimum, right, because you don't want the כהן kohen to get something
trivial that's not respectful. So in anything you would sort of think
that maybe you need the higher of the two, right, it has
to be a sixtieth and a and five סלע, sela, whichever is
larger, at least if you're able to give it. But anyway the
גמרא Gemara doesn't go because both of them are serving a different
purpose, right, one is serving the purpose of making sure you're giving
something that reflects the amount that you have to give. It's from
the perspective of the giver and the other's from the perspective of
the receiver. You want there to be some minimum amount. But anyway
the way the גמרא Gemara reconciles this is it says your obligation
is a sixtieth. That could be a trivial amount. But if it's
a lot and you're dividing it, then you have to pay attention
to give make sure it's respectable what you give to each person.
And don't give less than five סלע sela to each person. Yes.
Could that be a metaphor at all for obviously not the כהן,
kohen, but when you go to ישראל Yisrael and you have צדקה
tzedakah that you're giving to people that you don't try to give
it all to one?
Yeah, I mean I think that that's a point. Now the גמרא
Gemara does not say that you should subdivide it amongst many כהנים.
kohanim. I mean I actually think I said that when I was
paraphrasing the גמרא. Gemara. But the גמרא Gemara actually says that it
describes that you have decided you want to divide it up. So
the גמרא Gemara isn't saying you should divide it up. The גמרא
Gemara is saying if you've decided you want to divide it up,
then make sure you don't give you give each כהן kohen a
respectable amount. But that's a good question, a general question about הלכות
צדקה. Hilchos Tzedakah. About how do you do that? Well, you know,
do you give one person who really needs a lot? Do you
give a lot of people? Do you divide it? There is not
really a clear answer to that question and it is important, thanks
for pointing that out, but I misparaphrased the גמרא. Gemara. The גמרא
Gemara doesn't say you should divide it as if you're dividing it,
make sure each person gets a respectable amount. Okay, so, so that's
how the גמרא Gemara explains it. So now the way we've said
is the משנה Mishnah the minimum if you so now we're saying
according to one approach, the minimum is a sixtieth. A sixtieth.
And if however you have more than if a sixtieth translates into
more than five סלע, sela, then in a way that does have
both minimums. Then you start with the idea of a sixtieth, but
if that translates into more than five סלע, sela, right, then make
sure that you don't give any particular person less than five סלע.
sela. The other approach said no, it's always a flat minimum of
five סלע. sela. No even if you have even if the sixtieth
would produce even if you only have six סלע, sela, you still
have to give five סלע. sela. It has to be four סלע
sela as you did before.
Right, that's not clear.
Would they say that if you had thousands of סלעים sela'im would
they also say five סלע sela or would they agree that when
it goes to be more then they also would agree to that?
by different proportion. So the relationship of these two measures is not
clear. From one camp the approach is, if it produces less than
five סלע, sela, fine, give what you're able. If it produces more
than five סלע, sela, then the 60th measure, then make sure each
person doesn't get less. The other approach said no, you always have
to give five סלע. sela. What they don't what's not clear about
them is if you have thousands, do you only also only give
five סלע sela or then would you give?
Well, no, also if you have
less than that then you give everything that you have or you
leave yourself over a trivial amount, but you have to give as
close to five סלע sela as possible. Is there a פסק psak
on this? I'm sure there is. Then you have to give as
close to five סלע sela as possible. Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara goes on. So that is interesting, two different camps based on
two different ways of measuring. You know, I guess I'd also say
also, and this reflects back on the theme we had earlier, right?
If you remember about the importance about sort of, you know, giving
and receiving. Right, remember the whole discussion before was, on the one
hand, you don't leave it for the כהן, Kohen, you have responsibility
to find the כהן Kohen to give it. Your responsibility how you
give, but also their responsibility about how do they receive. Right? They
don't come up and demand, and you know, and the way they
even eat it has to be in a respectful way. So it's,
you know, looking at this from two perspectives. And here too, how
much do you give? Right, if you give a tiny bit, five
סלע, sela, and you have thousands and thousands of סלעים, selaim, that's
not that's not appropriate from the perspective of the giver, that you
haven't really done something appropriate. But also there's the question of the
perspective of the receiver, and they also, you know, from their perspective,
there has to be a minimum amount to be respected. So I
think it's very interesting looking at these transactions that they're the you
know, the way to assess them depends both on how it's given
and how it's received. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues the
following.
Where are we?
גופא, Gufo, let's look back at the debate. רב ושמואל אמרי תרווייהו,
Rav uShmuel amri tuvayhu, רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel both say, ראשית
הגז בשישים. Reishit HaGez beshishim. ראשית הגז Reishit HaGez is 1/60th minimum
and it's a proportion. Okay. תרומה בשישים. Terumah beshishim. תרומה Terumah is
a minimum of a 60th. פאה בשישים, Peah beshishim, and פאה Peah
is a 60th. So they all follow the same rule. Now the
גמרא Gemara is going to challenge this. תרומה בשישים? Terumah beshishim? תרומה
Terumah is a 60th? והנן תנן, v'anan tnan, תרומה עין יפה אחד
מארבעים, Terumah ayin yafah echad me'arba'im, a generous way of giving תרומה
Terumah is 1/40th. Okay. And it says an average way is a
50th, and a cheapskate way is a 60th. So why would they
say the cheapskate way? If that's, you know, why wouldn't they say
the generous or the average way? So the גמרא Gemara says: דאורייתא
בשישים. De'Oraita beshishim. Biblically 1/60th is enough.
Just wait. דרבנן בארבעים. De'Rabbanan be'arba'im. And rabbinically it's a 40th, and
they're giving you the minimum דאורייתא. De'Oraita. So the גמרא Gemara says
that's not true. דאורייתא בשישים? De'Oraita beshishim? Can you really say it's
60th? והאמר שמואל, ve'ha'amar Shmuel, doesn't שמואל Shmuel say חיטה אחת פוטרת
את הכרי? chita achat poteret ha'kari? That one grain exempts the entire,
you know, one piece one little grain exempts the entire mound of
wheat. So תרומה Terumah has no minimum amount biblically. So how can
you say the minimum is is a 60th? So the גמרא Gemara
says: All right, here's what we're going to say.
So דאורייתא כשמואל. De'Oraita k'Shmuel. Biblically שמואל Shmuel is right, one grain
can free for your whole granary. דרבנן בדאורייתא. De'Rabbanan b'De'Oraita. The rabbinic
שיעור shiur for biblical grain, for biblical produce, produce that is biblically
obligated in תרומה, Terumah, like, you know, like like the wheat and
barley and so on. So that is אחד מארבעים. echad me'arba'im. That
the ideal is 1/40th, at least that's the generous. דרבנן בדרבנן. De'Rabbanan
b'De'Rabbanan. However, the rabbinic amount for things that are rabbinically obligated in
תרומה. Terumah. What's only rabbinically obligated in תרומה? Terumah? The non-grains like
fruit. So fruit is only yeah, vegetables too so fruit is only
rabbinic. So therefore, there the Rabbis were more easy on you and
they gave as the minimum שישים, shishim, 1/60th. Okay, so that's a
new idea. We normally don't hear that. Normally we hear that the
average, the standard is a 50th, the generous is a 40th. But
here, at least רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel who are using a
60th, we're explaining it that when you deal with things that are
only rabbinically obligated we let you give only 1/60th.
Even for being generous.
Yeah, well that's at least the standard. I don't know generous, but
at least the standard. Now an interesting point here is, and this
goes also to the giver and the receiver,
that there are some אחרונים Acharonim who say that, you know, when
we say biblically it's one grain, there are two things you accomplish
by תרומה. Terumah. By תרומה, Terumah, first of all, you remove the
status of טבל tevel from the grain by designating this is תרומה,
Terumah, then the grain stops being טבל. tevel. I mean, actually you
have to take מעשר Ma'aser too, but it loses its its sort
of very weighty definition of טבל, tevel, the weightiest when you designate
תרומה. Terumah. So that's you make this sanctify this and it changes
the status of the grain. But there's so there's a מצווה mitzvah
to separate, but there's also a מצווה mitzvah to give it to
the כהן. Kohen. Okay, you make a ברכה bracha when you separate
the תרומה, Terumah, but there's also a מצווה mitzvah to give it
to the כהן. Kohen. And there it says ונתן. venatan. Remember before
we made דרשות drashas of ונתן venatan and emphasized what's an appropriate
amount and so on. So some say, I think the ערוך השולחן
Aruch HaShulchan says it, but I think many have said it before
him,
that biblically there's no minimum. minimum by תרומה terumah to do the
act of separating, to make the grain not טבל, tevel, but that
doesn't mean you've fulfilled ideally the מצוה mitzvah of giving to the
כהן. kohen. To fulfill the מצוה mitzvah of giving to the כהן,
kohen, it has to be something of significance and of substance. So
that already is similar to our similar whole type of a discussion,
right? There's what defines the act of sort of separating from your
perspective, and there's also what is the act of giving. There's a
difference to that though, because by us, by מתנות כהונה, matnot kehuna,
it's all about eventually giving to the כהן. kohen. There's really no
קדושה kedusha idea. So even when it's giving, you're talking what can
I afford and what's appropriate for you at the receiving end. Here
by תרומה terumah it's different. תרומה terumah there's an idea of designating
it to God, תרומה להשם, terumah l'Hashem, right? And designating it to
God, so there even a tiny bit has that significance of acknowledging
God and acknowledging, you know, that this, that you know, that you're
giving even anything is symbolic and has that acknowledgment. So there you
have the כל שהוא kol shehu at the act of separating, but
there still might be another שיעור shiur even biblically perhaps in terms
of what constitutes a significant act of giving. Yeah, Bobby.
When you were talking about receiving, that kind of fascinated me. Is
there someone supervising the כהנים kohanim to be sure that they're receiving
appropriate?
No. No. I mean, you know, I mean, if somebody sees it
and feels that it's not appropriate, you know, they might have, but
there's nobody who's walking around. I mean, first of all, they're receiving
this stuff all over the land, you know, so yeah.
We also mentioned that, you know, the בית דין Beit Din should
be supervising and give it to a worthy כהן. kohen.
Right, right, but how much that was actually done in practice, or
yeah.
So if I separate a single grain from my batch of wheat?
Yeah, you can't give more for the תרומה. terumah. Right, I'm thank
you for asking that. Meaning, what the ערוך השלחן Aruch HaShulchan and
others are saying is that once you've designated תרומה, terumah, then you're
stuck. That's it. So then you, right, right, thank you, I was
about meant to clarify that. So once you've designated that, you can't
now say, oh, but I have to give more to the כהן,
kohen, I'll give more to be nice. No, but they say if
you did that, you did the right, you made the grain not
טבל tevel and you did the מצוה mitzvah of separating תרומה, terumah,
but you have not ideally fulfilled the מצוה mitzvah of giving to
the כהן, kohen, but at that stage you can't fix it. But
if you separate more, then that's going to enable you to appropriately
do the מצוה mitzvah of giving to the כהן. kohen. And if
I take half
my grain and say this is תרומה? terumah?
That you could do.
I could do, but I...
Yeah, your families might go hungry.
But in these days, we don't know the כהנים kohanim and all
that, and you know, and the whole vegetable and fruit תרומה terumah
was rabbinic. So do we say you just keep it and eat
it yourself?
No,
no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no. The
whole thing about keeping it and מוציא מחברו עליו הראיה motzi mechavero
alav hara'aya is only by things that have no קדושה. kedusha. תרומה
terumah has קדושה. kedusha. If you eat תרומה terumah and you're
a non-כהן, kohen, you're חייב מיתה בידי שמים.
chayav mita bidei shamayim.
No, no, no, it doesn't matter, doesn't matter. We obviously we give
it, yeah, yeah.
So we do separate it these days?
You separate, well, you do a כל שהוא kol shehu because no
כהן kohen is losing out because you don't give it to a
כהן kohen anyway, all כהנים kohanim are טמאי מת, tmei meit, right?
And you do a כל שהוא kol shehu and yeah, I mean...
Is fruit any different than grain these days? No. Okay.
Yeah. I mean, there are some קולות kulot maybe about questions that
come up with certain ספק safek situations, like fruit juices and other
types of things, whether those are חייב chayav in תרומות terumot or
not. So there are some קולות kulot that come up by ספק
safek situations.
Yeah, I heard from Rabbi Slifkin that תרומה terumah in Israel is
fed to the animals at the zoo because the animals at the
zoo in Jerusalem are owned by a כהן. kohen.
Oh, that's very interesting. Okay, yeah.
What's a כל שהוא? kol shehu?
Even a tiniest amount.
Oh, and they put it on a coin these days, right?
No, the coin transfer you can't do with תרומה. terumah. That you
do with the מעשר שני. ma'aser sheni. מעשר שני. ma'aser sheni. Okay,
let's keep on going.
But what was wrong with saying a sixtieth? Yes, even if that
was my brain, if that's the minimum.
Right, so רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot explain why they wouldn't, why
it doesn't sound like רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel would have given,
you know, the amount that is sort of that is stingy and
that we are trying to discourage. But yeah, I understand. Let the
גמרא Gemara to this position.
So what do you give the תרומה? terumah?
You don't. You have to as you have to dispose of it
because nobody can eat it, and I just heard that they actually
feed it to animals that are owned by כהנים, kohanim, which is
what you can do to תרומה טמאה. terumah tmeiah. So that's a
very interesting solution. Okay. Moving on. Now the גמרא Gemara says פאה
בשישים, pe'ah b'shishim, פאה pe'ah is one-sixtieth. ותנן, v'tnan, we taught in
the משנה, Mishnah, didn't we teach in משנה Mishnah אלו דברים שאין
להם שיעור? elu devarim she'ein lahem shiur? The following things have no
minimum: הפאה והביכורים והראיון. hape'ah vehabikkurim vehare'ayon.
So פאה pe'ah and ביכורים, bikkurim, the amount you give for first
fruit, and appearing in the Temple for עולת ראיה olat re'iyah for
the רגל. regel. So not a sixtieth, it's no minimum. So the
גמרא Gemara says דאורייתא אין לה שיעור. de'oraita ein lah shiur. Yes,
biblically there is none. דרבנן בשישים, derabbanan b'shishim, rabbinically it's sixtieth. מאי
קמשמע לן? mai kamashma lan?
So what's that teaching you? תנינא, tanina, we taught that as well.
We taught in a משנה Mishnah אין פוחתין לפאה משישים, ein pochtin
l'pe'ah mishishim,
you don't give less than a sixtieth. So who needs רב Rav
and שמואל Shmuel to tell me this?
אף על פי שאמרו פאה אין לה שיעור, af al pi she'amru
pe'ah ein lah shiur, even though they said that there is no
minimum, you're supposed to give a sixtieth. So that exactly encapsulates that
idea that biblically there's no minimum, but rabbinically you're supposed to give
a sixtieth. So what are רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel teaching me?
So the גמרא Gemara says התם בארץ הכא בחוצה לארץ. hatam b'aretz
hacha b'chutz la'aretz. That's in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, but maybe in
חוץ לארץ chutz la'aretz when you give פאה—now pe'ah we don't give
פאה pe'ah here in חוץ לארץ, chutz la'aretz, but in the lands
near Israel. They applied some of the these gifts etcetera.
That’s what they mean by חוץ לארץ? chutz l'aretz?
Yes. So therefore there you would give, and the חידוש chidush is
that even there you give a sixtieth. Okay, so for פאה pe'ah
and תרומה terumah it's modifying some things that we pretty much knew,
but the major חידוש chidush is here for the ראשית הגז reishit
hagez that it is the משנה mishna would have you think it's
a bare minimum in absolute terms, and they're saying it's a proportional
amount, one sixtieth. All right, now the גמרא Gemara goes on. כי
סליק איסי בר היני, Ki salik Isi bar Hini, when איסי בר
היני Isi bar Hini went to ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, אשכחיה לרבי
יוחנן, ashkechei l'Rabbi Yochanan, he found רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, דקמתני ליה
לבריה, d'kamatni lei l'brei, that he was teaching his son, אשכחיה, ashkechei,
excuse me, there's not a ל lamed shouldn't be there. אשכחיה רבי
יוחנן, Ashkechei Rabbi Yochanan, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan found איסי בר היני,
Isi bar Hini, דקמתני ליה לבריה, d'kamatni lei l'brei, was teaching his
son the משנה. mishna. רחלים, rechelim, it says חמש רחלים, chamesh rechelim,
you need five sheep. So אמר ליה, amar lei, so רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan said to him, אתני רחלות, asni rachelot, you should say
רחלות rachelot in the feminine, not רחלים. rechelim. So he was correcting
his grammar, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan to איסי בר היני. Isi bar
Hini. אמר ליה, Amar lei, so
איסי בר היני Isi bar Hini said back to him, כדכתיב, kedichtiv,
I'm just following a פסוק. pasuk. רחלים מאתים, rechelim matayim, right? When
it talks about the gifts that יעקב Yaakov gave to עשו, Esav,
it says two hundred female sheep and it uses the masculine plural.
אמר ליה, Amar lei, he said back to him, לשון תורה לעצמה
לשון חכמים לעצמם. lashon Torah l'atzma lashon chachamim l'atzmam. Yes,
there's biblical grammar and there's rabbinic Hebrew and rabbinic grammar, and in
the rabbinic Hebrew we say רחלות. rachelot. Now of course it makes
sense because רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael
and he's an ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael native, so he knows, you
know, the common, he knows the spoken Hebrew of the and the
Mishnaic Hebrew, whereas איסי בר היני Isi bar Hini coming from בבל
Bavel maybe is not as fluent in Mishnaic Hebrew. So he's looking,
you know, this is what you do if you don't know, like
when I first went to ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael I didn't know
how, you know, and I was, I didn't know spoken Hebrew, I
kept on drawing on my rabbinic knowledge, you know, in order, so
I would, when I wanted to say money I said ממון. mamon.
It
was
quite funny. Anyway, so here if you don't know, if you don't
know Tannaitic Hebrew, you're drawn on biblical Hebrew. So he was using
a biblical word, he was saying רחלים, rechelim, and רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan was saying it's very nice but here we say רחלות, rachelot,
that's Tannaitic Hebrew, that's, that's Mishnaic Hebrew. Okay, so that was that
exchange.
אמר ליה, Amar lei, so, אמר ליה, amar lei, so then רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said to him, not clear this setting, another setting,
presumably this one, מאן ריש סידרא בבבל? man reish sidra b'Vavel? Who
is like the ראש ישיבה Rosh Yeshiva there in בבל? Bavel?
Meaning like why aren't you being taught properly?
Not, not clear what motivated the question. אמר ליה, Amar lei, he
said back to him, אבא אריכא, Abba Aricha, the tall אבא. Abba.
Now אבא Abba is רב, Rav, רב Rav is actually as we
heard the other night in the lecture from Dr. Elman, רב אבא
Rav Abba is רב. Rav. Okay, so that was, so but his
first name was אבא. Abba. So אבא אריכא, Abba Aricha, the tall
אבא, Abba, and he was very tall. אמר ליה, Amar lei, so
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said to him, אבא אריכא קרית ליה? Abba
Aricha karyat lei? You're calling him אבא Abba the tall one? So
that, I mean, that's the way you, I'm sorry, excuse me, I
made a mistake, okay, because רבא Rava would have, is much later
than רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, excuse me, so רב, Rav, no, רבא
Rava is also the name אבא, Abba, but רב Rav would have
also name אבא Abba was a very common name. Right, right, right.
Okay, anyway, אבא אריכא, Abba Aricha, אבא Abba the tall one, which
was רב. Rav. Okay, so anyway, אבא אריכא, Abba Aricha, אבא Abba
the tall one. אמר ליה, Amar lei, so רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
said back to him, אבא אריכא קרית ליה? Abba Aricha karyat lei?
You're calling him אבא Abba the tall one? Is that how you
talk about your רבי? Rebbi? So דכירנא, dachirna, I remember, כד הוינא
יתיבנא אחורי י"ז שורן אחורי דרב, kad havina yasivna acharei yod zayin
shuran acharei d'Rav, when I,
when רב Rav was here in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, because רב
Rav started in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and he went to בבל,
Bavel, I remember when רב Rav was here in ארץ ישראל, Eretz
Yisrael, he was at the head of the class, I was seventeen
rows behind him, says רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, I was seventeen rows
behind רב, Rav, קמיה דרבי, kamei d'Rebbi, and רב Rav was in
front of רבי, Rebbi, right, these are all the first generation of
אמוראים Amoraim after רבי, Rebbi, רב Rav and רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan.
I was seventeen back and he was in front of רבי Rebbi
and I was seventeen rows behind him, ונפיק זיקוקין דנור מפומיה דרב
לפומיה דרבי, v'nafik zikukin d'nur mipumei d'Rav l'pumei d'Rebbi,
and like sparks of light were coming out of the mouth of
רב Rav to רבי Rebbi and back and forth, he doesn't mean
it literally, like a fire, whatever, like little fla, you know, little
bolts of lightning essentially, meaning that they were talking in very, you
know, elevated terms and, and לפומיה דרבי לפומיה דרב l'pumei d'Rebbi l'pumei
d'Rav
back and forth, you know, it was this flashes of lights back
and forth, ולא הוה ידענא מאי קאמרי, v'la hava yadana mai ka'amri,
and I had no idea what they were talking about, right, there
was a totally different plane than me, I couldn't understand what was
going on, and that's who רב Rav is, that's who your ראש
ישיבה Rosh Yeshiva is. ואת אבא אריכא קרית ליה? V'at Abba Aricha
karyat lei? You're so familiar with him and you call him, oh,
אבא Abba the tall one? So he's twice correcting him, one grammar
and the other is just a respectful way of speaking, but it
matters how you talk, is what he's saying. Okay, it matters how
you, how you refer to things. So אמר ליה, amar lei, okay,
so then he said, look, obviously you don't know your grammar, you
don't know, you don't know how to talk about people respectfully, let's
talk about הלכה, halacha, let's talk about תורה. Torah. So אמר ליה
איהו ראשית הגז בכמה? amar lei ihu reishit hagez b'chama? So actually,
so then he said, so Where are we? Okay,
I'm sorry, excuse me, רב Rav איסי *Rav Issi* said, I'm sorry,
I got the people wrong. רב Rav איסי *Rav Issi* now said
to רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*, maybe he tried to switch the topic,
so he said, let's talk in learning. Okay, so how much do
you give for ראשית הגז reishit hagez. *Reishis HaGeiz*? אמר ליה *Amar
lei*, so he said, אמר ליה רבי יוחנן *amar lei Rabbi Yochanan*,
so רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* said back to him, בששים *beshishim*, you
give, you give a sixtieth. Okay, or it's not exactly clear if
ששים *shishim* here means a sixtieth because if you remember back, רבי
יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* was the one that said, actually רבי יוחנן *Rabbi
Yochanan*, well actually רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* was the one that said
that you give a minimum of, you give, you give five. Right,
you give five, but anyway we're going to deal with that, we're
going to deal with that in a minute. But let's say now
means a sixtieth or you need sixty to start with, okay? But
it better reads, רש"י Rashi *Rashi* has both explanations, but it better
reads a sixtieth. So then, והנן בכלשהו תנן *va'anan b'kholshehu tnan*, so
איסי בר יהודה *Issi bar Yehuda* said to רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*,
but the משנה Mishna, *Mishnah* says even a tiniest amount? How could
you say you can start with a tiniest amount, which obviously, so
how can you say you need to start with sixty or how
do you say you give a sixtieth? So אמר ליה *amar lei*,
he said back to him, אם כן מה בין לי ולך *im
kein ma bein li velakh*. I also know how to read a
משנה mishnah *Mishnah*. If that's all I can do is say what
the משנה mishnah *Mishnah* says, then what difference, you know, what's the
difference between me and you? I obviously can think beyond what the
משנה Mishnah. *Mishnah* is saying and I realize that even though the
משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* says כלשהו *kolshehu*, there's more to be said about
it. Okay, so here he wasn't letting him get out of just
like it maybe seems like איסי בן יהודה *Issi ben Yehuda* was
trying to, you know, up him or something, at least show that
he knew תורה Torah *Torah* and could challenge him, but רבי יוחנן
*Rabbi Yochanan* wasn't having any of it. רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* said,
look, I also know how to read a משנה Mishna. *Mishnah*. Okay,
you know, and he said, but nevertheless, I say sixtieth. So now
this is the question, right, how do you have both of them?
So that's the issue that we said before, meaning even though the
משנה Mishna *Mishnah* said a כלשהו *kolshehu*, you could start with כלשהו
*kolshehu*, we said before כלשהו *kolshehu* doesn't literally mean כלשהו *kolshehu*. כלשהו
*Kolshehu* means enough to mean it's a trivial amount relative to the
amount that was said before, okay, but enough to produce, it might
still be the sixty סלע sela. *sela*, it might still be not
a literal כלשהו *kolshehu*, still the sixty סלע sela. *sela*, which is
enough to produce one סלע sela, *sela* as a result if you
do one sixtieth. So now the גמרא Gmara *Gemara* goes on and
says the following. That was the end of that. That was the
end of that exchange. But now we're going to deal with the
idea that before רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* said that you start with
six and here he's saying sixty or a sixtieth depending on how
you read it. So כי אתא רב Rav דימי אמר ראשית הגז
*ki ata Rav Dimi amar Reishis HaGeiz*, so when רב Rav. דימי
*Rav Dimi* came from ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael* he said, ראשית הגז
*Reishis HaGeiz* how much? רב Rav, אמר בששים *Rav amar beshishim*, רב
Rav *Rav* says you, again ששים *shishim* is always not clear if
it means sixty סלע sela *sela* or one sixtieth, but it's the
same basic position, at least that's what we've seen so far. If
you give one sixtieth, you want to end up with one סלע
sela, *sela* and therefore you have to start with sixty סלע sela.
*sela*. So sixty refers to both aspects, could easily refer to both
aspects. רש"י Rashi *Rashi* has two explanations. So anyway, sixtieth or starting
with sixty. רבי יוחנן משום רבי ינאי אמר בשש *Rabbi Yochanan mishum
Rabbi Yannai amar beshesh*. And this is the position we quoted earlier
for רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*, it's enough to start with six and
you give five because you give an absolute minimum, you don't give
a sixtieth. So אמר ליה אביי לרב דימי אנחת לן חדא ואקצצת
לן חדא *amar lei Abaye le-Rav Dimi anachta lan khada ve-aktasta lan
khada*. So אביי *Abaye* said to רב Rav, דימי *Rav Dimi* who
reported it, one of these things you said makes sense, the other
is difficult. Why? Both of them at least prima facie are difficult.
Why? Because here you're quoting רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* who says you
start with six, but we just had a minute before with that
whole fascinating and funny exchange of רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* and איסי
*Issi*, רב איסי *Rav Issi*, that he said ששים *shishim*, right? So
which is it? Is it six or sixty? So he says בשלמא
דרבי יוחנן אדרבי יוחנן לא קשיא *bishlama de-Rabbi Yochanan ad-Rabbi Yochanan lo
kashya*, so those are, even though רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* seems to
contradict, that we can get out of, why? הא דידיה הא דרביה
*ha didei ha de-rabbei*. One he said, here it says רבי יוחנן
*Rabbi Yochanan* in the name of רבי ינאי *Rabbi Yannai* says six,
and the other was רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*'s own position. So רבי
יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* in the name of רבי ינאי *Rabbi Yannai*, that
was the idea of six, his own position was ששים *shishim*. אלא
דרב אדרב קשיא *Ela de-Rav ad-Rav kashya*, but we have a contradiction
of רב *Rav*. Here you quoted רב *Rav* saying ששים *shishim*, והא
אמר רב מנה mane. ופרס *ve-ha amar Rav mane u-pras*, because רב
*Rav* also says one and a half מנה mane, *mane*. Now, why,
now again, this is getting a little confusing because the question is
are we talking about proportion or are we talking about absolute? Let
me just take a step back and review.
The משנה Mishna. *Mishnah* said כלשהו *kolshehu*. You start with a כלשהו
*kolshehu*. Okay, that was what איסי בן יהודה *Issi ben Yehuda* was
challenging רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* about. He says כלשהו *kolshehu* literally means
כלשהו *kolshehu*. Nevertheless, although there are those that say כלשהו *kolshehu* literally
does mean כלשהו *kolshehu*, overwhelmingly
there's a desire to interpret it as being some minimum amount of
significance. And we had a couple of opinions, right? We had a
position of one and a half מנה mane *mane*, okay, as the
amount, which was not clear in terms of what it would produce,
it just seems to be an amount. And then we had two
other positions. One which was ששים *shishim*, which if you went by
proportion would produce a, would produce one סלע sela. *sela*, and one
which was שש *shesh*, which if you went by an absolute minimum
would allow you to give five and keep one. So those were
basically the three positions other than a literal כלשהו *kolshehu*. But a
literal כלשהו *kolshehu* is what רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* says, look, I
know how to read a משנה Mishna *Mishnah* too, but I don't
think it means it literally. Okay, so then you had, so then
you had the three positions: one and a half מנה mane *mane*,
ששים *shishim* which produces one, and שש *shesh* which, which then you
would give five because you, that would be different approaches whether you
give proportion or whether you give absolute. So now we've got a
problem. רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* said both of the last two opinions.
In one place he said ששים *shishim* in order to give proportion
and give one, and in another place he said שש *shesh* in
order to give an absolute minimum of five. גמרא Gmara *Gemara* said
that we can reconcile because that one he said in the name
of his רב *Rav* and one he said on his own opinion.
But now we have a problem about רב *Rav*. Because רב in
one place said the idea of, here רב was quoted as saying
sixty in order to produce one, but רב at the top of
the page said one and a half מנה. mane So how you
going to reconcile that? Okay, so let's take a look. So the
גמרא Gmara says רב אדרב נמי לא קשיא, Rav a-de-Rav nami lo
kashya, that's not a problem.
מאי מנה דקאמר בין ארבעים סלעים. Mai mane de-ka'amar ben arba'im sela'im.
When he said one and a half מנה, mane so normally a
מנה mane? is twenty-five סלע. sela. But apparently there was some type
of a מנה mane. that was forty סלע. sela. So if you
did one and a half מנה mane of a forty סלע, sela
then that gives you how much? Math everybody, one and a half
times forty, sixty. So that is consistent with רב's other claim of
sixty. Okay, so that is what רב. Let's just finish that up.
דהוה ליה בשיתים, De-have leh be-shishim, that's sixty. So then גמרא Gmara
says ותני תנא מנה בין ארבעים סלעים? Ve-tani tana mane ben arba'im
sela'im? Would the תנא tana when he talks about מנה mane ever
be referring to a forty סלע sela מנה? mane Maybe it exists,
but it's very unusual, it's very rare. Why would he be talking
about that? Now the interesting thing is, okay, let's just say this.
So the גמרא Gmara says אין, In, yes. התנן Ha-tenan or it
should be ותניא, Ve-tanya, anyway we taught in the משנה, mishnah
or a ברייתא Baraisa really, it's a תוספתא. Tosefta. חימת חדשה, Chemat
chadasha, if you have a flask of like that normally holds water
of, אף על פי שמקבלת רימונים, af al pi she-mekabeles rimonim, but
it hasn't been sewn up yet. So it's got a hole in
it, right, where on the where you would sew it up, on
the what's it called, not the crease, the seam, thank you. So
you haven't finished sewing yet, but you could still use it to
hold pomegranates because it's got to be a pretty big hole for
a pomegranate to fall through. So is that considered yet a vessel?
So the answer is no. Until you're done making it, even if
it could function in some way, it's not yet a vessel. So
טהורה, tehora, it cannot become טמא. tame. תפרה, tefara, you sewed it
and then it became a vessel. Now it retains the status of
a vessel longer once it got the status. So now that it
became a vessel ונקראה ve-nikre'a and it tore, שיעורה כמוציא רימונים. shi'ura
ke-motzi rimonim. As long as it can still hold pomegranates and they
won't fall out, it'll still be considered a vessel. So but when
before it was finished being able to hold pomegranates did not give
it the status, it had to be finished. Once it got the
status, it won't lose the status until the hole is so big
that pomegranates would fall out. Okay, so far it's not relevant to
us. רבי אלעזר בן יעקב אומר כפקעיות של שתי. Rabbi Elazar ben
Yaakov omer ke-paka'iyos shel shesi. It doesn't have to be able to
hold pomegranates, or that's not enough, those are huge and you normally
wouldn't use it for that even בשעת הדחק, be-sha'as ha-dechak, even if
you didn't have alternatives. But what you'd have to be able to
hold, what you might use it for, is the little, what is
it called, spindles, the things, what, shuttles, that's the thing that they
would do when they were making the warp, they throw the, it's
a shuttle, right, yes. So a shuttle of the warp or the
woof, I keep on getting mixed up which is שתי. shesi. Anyway,
so it has to be able to hold those shuttles, okay. It
can't be a hole so big that it just holds a pomegranate,
it has to be a hole that can hold these shuttles.
וכמה אחת מארבעה במנה בין ארבעים סלעים. Ve-kama achas me-arba'ah be-mane ben
arba'im sela'im. How big are these things? I know. These things are
as big as a quarter of a of a of a אחת
מארבעה, achas me-arba'ah,
it's a quarter of a סלע, sela the types of סלעים sela'im
of which forty of which make up a מנה. mane Okay, so
anyway, the point is he is talking about a certain type of
a מנה mane, made out of forty סלע. sela So you see
every now and then we have talk about a מנה mane made
out of forty סלע. sela. Of course, as Michael said, he explicitly
had to say that he was talking about a מנה mane that
is made up of forty סלע. sela, Normally we would assume we're
talking about a מנה mane, made up of twenty-five סלע. sela, Either
way, we use this to reconcile רב, so רב that says one
and a half מנה, mane right, that seems like a very arbitrary
amount, now we have translated it into an amount that makes somewhat
of sense. If the מנה mane is not a twenty-five סלע sela.
מנה maneh, but a forty סלע sela. מנה, maneh one and a
half becomes sixty, which allows us to produce one סלע sela. at
the end. So the upshot of all of this is, is there
a minimum amount that you have to shear the sheep? Maybe it's
just in terms of saying, forget what you're giving, just to make
it considered like it's something substantive that you sheared. That seems to
be our point of departure, and that's where we got one and
a half מנה per sheep, one and a half מנה total. But
then very quickly we move into having enough shearing so that what
you're able to give has some significance. And then it's a function
of whether you think what you give is a proportion, one sixtieth,
so then we, the גמרא Gemara goes to sort of saying one
סלע is where you start, you work backwards to get to sixty,
that's רב, that's what we quoted before, that was earlier opinions. Or
do you start by saying five as an absolute amount, not a
proportional amount, and then all you need is six. And those seem
to be the two dominant positions, but then the גמרא Gemara, also
is trying to reconcile how maybe you go by both minimums. You
start with the idea of proportion, if that leads to a lot,
then make sure to any individual person you don't give less than
five סלע.
Yes, and since this is not actual קדוש kadosh and it's more
of a matter of separating it and giving and having someone give,
you know, get something, so then if your, you know, first shearings
go and get mixed up with everything and then you just like,
you know, and you were giving let's say five, just whatever it
is, then you just go out and just take any five, right,
and just give that to him?
Or does the whole thing just, you know, gets null and void
and you don't need to give it anymore, or or there's a
problem with everything?
One more time?
What? There's you've always
ratioed.
Oh, so that's an interesting question whether there's any concept of status
or there's no of it being designated as such or does it
not have any status until you actually give it to him? To
some degree that was also the question before about מתנות כהונה נגזלות
matnot kehunah nigzalot and so on. That is a good question, meaning
if I designated it off and it before I gave it to
him it got destroyed in a fire, do I have to give
him other stuff because I haven't yet given it to him? Or
does the fact that I designated that already sort of makes it
his and so on? So to some degree the indication earlier was
that the sense of separating it does make it owned, does make
it theirs already because that's the, you know, מתנות כהונה נגזלות matnot
kehunah nigzalot or, you know, מזיק מתנות כהונה mazik matnot kehunah discussion.
Right, but that is a good question about a status without קדושה.
kedushah. Yes, Bobby.
Did the כהנים kohanim wear separate garments than everyone else so everyone
knows this is a כהן kohen and I can give this to
him?
Well, not not outside of the בית המקדש, Beit ha-Mikdash, but he
would be known socially, you
know, even if, you
know, he goes into a different community.
Right, and then there would be there are discussions in the גמרא
Gemara about, you know, who do you give תרומה terumah to because
of because it because can you give תרומה terumah to the slave
of a כהן kohen because then people will think that the slave
is a כהן? kohen? So about how sort of socially we are
sensitive to the signs that we're sending, you know, signals that we're
sending about who and who's not a כהן. kohen. Yeah, but people
would have to, you know, establish themselves or be known and exactly.
Okay, yeah, Charlie.
The
פחד
יצחק, Pachad Yitzchak,
is there a source that describes the different weights and measures and
when they
changed?
It is very confusing. Not in the גמרא, Gemara like there's some
good reference works that give basic tables like, what's his name,
not Jastrow. First of all, there's the Frank, which is like this
more sort of, you know, simple dictionary, much simpler than Jastrow, and
in the back of it it has good charts, and also שטיינזלץ
Steinsaltz in his volume of introduction of his introductory volume תלמוד Talmud
has charts in the back. So there are things that have good
charts. In terms of like academic work that actually describes what the
whole coinage system was and how things evolved, I'm sure there is
but I don't know it off the top of my head. Yes.
Michael's question, so תרומה, terumah, which is a sanctified, you separate it
and then it gets lost?
Then you're done. And it gets mixed up, it gives it makes
a whole problem with your grain because now it has תרומה terumah
mixed up into it. Right, but this, that is a very good
question and the sense here from earlier משניות mishnayot is yes, that
it does have that status once you've separated it even before you've
given it.
But if it falls into your stuff?
Then it's like a המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה ha-motzi me-chavero alav ha-re'ayah
type of a thing. You would just keep it all? Well, no,
because that might be משתרשי ליה mishtarshi lei and so on. So
what do you do? So then you would maybe give other stuff
in exchange or whatever. But anyway, all right, now we move on.
By the way, again, I'm sorry because I'm getting confused with the
whole thing with the proportions. When it said אחת מארבעים מנה, achat
me-arba'im maneh, it's not a quarter of a סלע, it is it
is a quarter of a מנה, which is a מנה made out
of forty סלע, meaning that he says that the size of this
thing would be ten סלע. Right, right, so I think I might
have explained it wrong. Okay, anyway, moving on. Okay, וכמה נותן לו,
ve-kamah noten lo, how much do you give him? It says enough
that now we're back to the absolute minimum, it says חמש סלעים,
chamesh sela'im, enough to make out of it a laundered, enough to
make out of it a little garment. So the funny thing was
was the beginning of the משנה says laundered and then it says
if you if you dyed it, you then that's another example that
it already has its status before you give it. It says if
you dyed it then then you've taken possession of it and and
you don't and you don't give it to him. But it says
but if you laundered it then you still give it to him,
which makes it sound like you're not supposed to launder it, only
if you laundered it. So how does that fit with the beginning
of the משנה that says how much do you give him? חמש
סלעים chamesh sela'im worth laundered enough to make a small garment. So
let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. So the גמרא Gemara says
וכמה נותן לו, ve-kamah noten lo, תנו tanu we taught in a
ברייתא, braita, לא שילבננו ויתננו לו, lo she-yilbenenu ve-yitnenu lo, not that
you first launder it and then give it to him afterwards, you
give it to him raw. So what does it mean then?
אלא שילבננו כהן ויעמוד על חמש סלעים, ela she-yilbenenu kohen ve-ya'amod al
chamesh sela'im, you have to give him enough raw wool that after
he processes it and launders it it can then turn into חמש
סלעים. chamesh sela'im. But you are supposed to give him to raw.
You don't play with it, again this goes also back this also
goes back to Michael's point, you know, which is is that once
you separate it it's his and then you don't touch it because
then it's his, you know, you're not supposed to handle it. Okay,
and if you actually dye it then you would have stolen it
from him.
Right, exactly. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says כדי לעשות בגד
קטן, kedei la'asot beged katan, enough to make a small garment. מנא
הני מילי, mena hanei milei, how do you know that that's the
minimum and that it's important to give it to him that minimum
so he can make a small garment? So אמר רבי יהושע בן
לוי, amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, אמר קרא amar kra because the
פסוק pasuk says לעמוד לשרת, la-amod le-sharet, in order that he
could it
says because God has chosen him to stand and to serve. דבר
שהוא ראוי לשירות, davar she-hu ra'uy le-sheirut, something that is fit for
serving in the בית המקדש. Beit ha-Mikdash. So we're going to say
in a minute that that would be the belt that the כהן
kohen would wear and that the amount of wool that it would
take now That belt was not made only out of wool, that
belt was made of a combination of wool and linen, but the,
so it's interesting, it's not that you could make an entire garment
out of it, but the amount of wool that would go into
that would be could be as little as five סלע.
It was a very long belt, apparently.
Maybe it's very thin. So the גמרא Gemara says מאי ניהו mai
nihu and what would that be, the smallest amount? אבנט, avnet, the
belt. So the גמרא Gemara. says אימא מעיל, eima me'il, maybe it's
a big, it's the whole, you know, cloak. How do you, why
do you interpret it only as the small one? So the גמרא
Gemara says no, תפסת מרובה לא תפסת, תפסת מועט תפסת. tafasta meruba
lo tafasta, tafasta muat tafasta. A very famous line of the גמרא.
Gemara If you grab a lot, you haven't grabbed. If you grab
a little, then you've grabbed. Meaning, don't overreach. Right? If you claim
that it means something big, maybe it doesn't, you can't prove your
case, so you'll have to like, you'll have to give it back.
Like, you know, if like if you put candy on the table
and some kid like tries to grab as much as possible, parent
is going to say, oh, you took too much, give it back.
So that's תפסת מרובה לא תפסת. tafasta meruba lo tafasta. If you
try to grab too much, you're not going to be able to
keep it. Okay? If you grab only a little, you know you'll
be able to keep it. So don't overreach. It says a garment,
we don't know how big, we have to assume the minimum. All
right. So the גמרא Gemara says ואימא כיפה של צמר, ve'eima kippah
shel tzemar, maybe it is a little wool כיפה. kippah. Okay, that's
interesting. Since when do כהנים kohanim wear a כיפה? kippah? So let's
take a look. דתניא, detanya, we learned in a ברייתא, Baraisa, כיפה
של צמר, kippah shel tzemar, what? A wool כיפה, kippah, literally כיפה
kippah like a little thing on the head. Okay, היתה מונחת בראש
כהן גדול, haysa munachas berosh kohen gadol, was on the head of
the כהן גדול, kohen gadol, ועליה ציץ נתון, ve'aleha tzitz nasun, and
the ציץ tzitz would be on it, לקיים מה שנאמר, lekayem mah
shene'emar, to fulfill the verse that says, ושמת אותו, vesamta oso, you
shall place it, the ציץ, tzitz, על פתיל תכלת, al pesil techeiles,
on a blue string. Now we normally assume what that means is
is that you have a blue string which sort of, you know,
which sort of secures the ציץ tzitz like at the back of
the head. But this actually is reading that there's some type of
a little blue thing that the כהן kohen keeps like a little
כיפה kippah here, not here or here, whatever, and the ציץ tzitz
is and that's the blue string on his forehead essentially and the
ציץ tzitz is actually what?
It's a big בוכרי. Buchari.
Maybe like that. Okay, but then and that's where the ציץ tzitz
goes on. Now this is very bizarre, we never assume this, whatever,
you know, the רמב"ם Rambam doesn't bring this גמרא Gemara down, he
never says this, but this גמרא Gemara is at least saying that
the כהן גדול kohen gadol would have a little כיפה kippah that
he would that he would put on his forehead.
What exactly is it?
The ציץ tzitz is a is a gold metal like a tiara.
What? No, not a well, sort of, but it's like it's a
flat metal plate, thin flat, you know, curved metal plate. It would
say קודש לה' Kodesh L'Hashem on it. Well, the question is, right,
how would he secure it? So normally this verse is read is
that there's a string maybe that, you know, is maybe there are
holes in it or whatever that would secure it. The כיפה kippah
is this is reading it very differently. It's not dealing with how
it would secure it. It's just saying that if it says on
a string, it's reading the כיפה kippah as the string, that there's
some little some little thread, some little, you know, piece of blue
garment that it would be on that would be touching between him
and his forehead.
Artscroll was calling it a ribbon, which is very different.
Well, that's why well, but it's calling it a ribbon because it's
trying it is more elegant and it's trying to bridge the gap
between between string and כיפה. kippah. כיפה kippah isn't a string. So
if you call it a ribbon, it's somewhere in that middle space.
It's not a string, it's not a כיפה, kippah, it's a ribbon.
That's a nice translation. What?
Plus made out of wool. How do you have a ribbon made
out of wool?
Right. Right. So anyway, they're just trying to describe something that is
midway between a כיפה kippah and a string. Okay, anyway, whatever. Moving
on. So the גמרא Gemara says אמר קרא, amar kra, the verse
says no, הוא ובניו, hu uvanav, that he got his chosen him
and his sons. דבר השוה לאהרן ולבניו, davar hashaveh le'Aharon ulevanav, only
something that's equivalent for them and the the other כהנים kohanim did
not wear this little כיפה. kippah. So the גמרא Gemara says אבנט
נמי לא שוו, avnet nami lo shavu, one minute, they didn't all
wear the same type of belt. What does that mean? הניחא למאן
דאמר אבנטו של כהן גדול לא זהו אבנטו של כהן הדיוט. hanicha
leman de'amar avneto shel kohen gadol lo zehu avneto shel kohen hedyot.
שפיר. Shapir. Now the כהן גדול kohen gadol on יום כיפור Yom
Kippur wore a belt that was all linen. Okay, the כהן גדול
kohen gadol during the year wore a belt that was שעטנז, shatnez,
wool and linen. What's not clear is what was the belt that
a normal כהן kohen wore. Was it like the כהן גדול kohen
gadol on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, all linen, or was it like
the כהן גדול kohen gadol during the rest of the year, wool
and linen? Now for our purposes, we'd like it to be wool
and linen because we're trying to say that you use the wool
that goes into the belt and a belt that was done equally
with אהרן Aharon and his children. So the גמרא Gemara says it
makes sense, הניחא למאן דאמר אבנטו של כהן גדול לא זהו אבנטו
של כהן הדיוט, hanicha leman de'amar avneto shel kohen gadol lo zehu
avneto shel kohen hedyot, that the אבנט avnet of a כהן גדול
kohen gadol meaning on יום כיפור Yom Kippur was not the same
as a normal כהן, kohen, that a normal כהן kohen would not
wear linen but would wear wool and linen. Then it works.
שפיר, Shapir, works. אלא למאן דאמר זהו אבנטו של כהן הדיוט, ela
leman de'amar zehu avneto shel kohen hedyot, if you say that the
normal כהן kohen would wear a linen belt like the כהן גדול
kohen gadol on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, so then you don't have
the wool used in something that's used equally by the כהן גדול
kohen gadol and the other כהנים, kohanim, right, because the belt you
only have the wool used in the כהן גדול's kohen gadol belt,
you don't have the wool used in the other כהנים's kohanim belt.
So the גמרא Gemara says מאי איכא למימר, mai ika lemeimar, what
can you say? So the גמרא Gemara says שם אבנט בעולם. shem
avnet ba'olam. Nevertheless, all כהנים kohanim wear a belt. They don't all
wear the same material, but it says you have to be able
to use this for a garment. What type of a garment? A
garment that all... Kohanim wear? So that's not this כיפה. kippah. What
is that garment? It's the smallest garment, a belt. And since at
least in one case it has wool, that's what we're going to
use to determine the amount. And that's how we get our minimum
of the five סלע. Okay, now, לא הספיק ליתנו לו. lo hispik
litno lo. Now it talks about you did not give it to
him till you dyed it. איתמר. itmar.
Now we're going to talk about another case about maybe getting out
of having to give it to him. There you designated and then
you essentially stole it by dyeing it. But let's have another case.
גזז ומכר ראשונה. gazaz umachar rishona. So let's say you had your
five sheep, you sheared one and you sold that wool. You sheared
the next and you sold that wool. So by the time you
got to the fifth sheep, you did not have five shearings still
in your possession. Are you obligated or exempt? Okay? גזז ומכר ראשונה,
gazaz umachar rishona, you sheared and you sold the first before you
got to the later sheep. רב חסדא אמר חייב, Rav Chisda amar
chayav, you still have to pay. רב נתן בר הושעיא אמר פטור,
Rav Natan bar Oshaya amar patur, you're exempt. רב חסדא אמר חייב,
Rav Chisda amar chayav, you're obligated, דהא גזז, de-ha gazaz, in the
end of the day you sheared five sheep, even if you didn't
at any one time have all of the shearings in your possession.
רב נתן בר הושעיא אמר פטור, Rav Natan bar Oshaya amar patur,
you're exempt, בעידנא דקמלי שיעורא, be-idna de-kamlei shiura, by the time that
the minimum amount has been filled when you have the five shearings,
בעינן צאנך, be'inan tzoncha, they still have to be your sheep, וליכא,
ve-leika, and they are not. So that actually sounds like you, yeah,
so right. So that, let me just check רש"י Rashi because I'm
pretty sure רש"י said that you sold the shearings, but that's making
it sound like you sold the sheep. Hold on.
No, no, I so I misexplained, I mistranslated.
רש"י says, excuse me, that you actually what you did is you
didn't sell the shearings, I'm sorry, my mistake, you didn't sell the
shearings, you actually sold the sheep. Okay, so that's also after you
sheared it. You sheared it and then you sold the sheep, right.
So you did have the five shearings at the end, you had
the minimum amount of shearings all in your possession, but it wasn't,
but you didn't have all five sheep in your possession after you
had sheared them. Right, you don't have a flock. Right. Okay, you
just kept the shearings. Right. I said you sold the shearings. I
don't know. Let's focus. Okay, so that's what you did. So, so,
you reset. Okay, you sheared it, you sold some of the sheep
before you finished shearing, you had all of the shearings in your
possession, but you didn't have at that stage צאנך, tzoncha, you didn't
have all of the sheep. So that's the debate. Does it, do
you just need it when to have the sheep when you're shearing
them or even at the end when you have all the shearings?
So, so he says פטור, patur, בעידנא דקמלי שיעורא, be-idna de-kamlei shiura,
when the time the minimum amount is satisfied, בעינן צאנך, be'inan tzoncha,
you need them in your possession, וליכא, ve-leika, and you don't have
it. Okay, תנא. tna. We taught in the משנה. הלוקח גז צאנו
של עובד כוכבים פטור מראשית הגז. halokeach gez tzono shel oved kochavim
patur me-reishit hagez. If you buy the shearings from the non-Jew, you're
exempt from ראשית הגז. Now, buying the shearings here are two scenarios.
The simple scenario is the non-Jew already sheared it and you buy
it from him, then obviously you're exempt, you didn't shear your sheep.
Okay, but it even means you bought the shearings while they're still
on the sheep. A non-Jew comes to me with these sheep filled
with wool and I said, I will buy the shearings from, I'm
buying the shearings from you right now and then I go and
I shear them and I keep the shearings, okay? I bought the
shearings on the sheep themselves. Even in that case, the משנה says
you're exempt. Why? Because it's not צאנך, tzoncha, okay? Even though you
did the shearing. So that's the case you're exempt. So it says
like this:
פטור מראשית הגז. patur me-reishit hagez. הצאנו לגזוז, hatzono ligzoz, let's say
I bought the sheep from the non-Jew, not full ownership of the
sheep, but I bought him for the purpose of shearing, right? We
discussed that before, like a tree for its fruit. I bought the
sheep for the purpose of shearing. In that type of a case,
I would be obligated because when I'm shearing it, it is my
sheep. So חייב, chayav, you'd be חייב. chayav. אמאי, amai, why is
that true? כחד וחד בתר גיזה נפקי ליה מרשותיה. kochad vechad batar
giza nafkei lei me-reshutei. Since I'm buying it for the shearing, I
take sheep number one, as soon as I do the shearing, at
the end of sheep number one, who owns that sheep? After I'm
done with shearing sheep number one, then it goes back to the
non-Jew. I only bought it for the purpose of shearing. So that's
exactly our case. But after you're done shearing, you don't own the
sheep anymore because they immediately revert back. So by the time you're
done with shearing all five sheep, you don't own, you no longer
own the five sheep because as soon as you're done, they revert
back to the non-Jew. And you see nevertheless you're חייב chayav since
you owned it at the time of shearing, even if you didn't
own it at the end. So the גמרא Gemara says,
תרגמה רב חסדא אליבא דרב נתן בר הושעיא. targema Rav Chisda aliba
de-Rav Natan bar Oshaya. So רב חסדא Rav Chisda sort of came
to the defense of his בר פלוגתא, bar plugta, says yeah, you
can get out of that. Why? כגון שהקנה לו כל שלשים יום.
kegon she-hikna lo kol shloshim yom. Even though we're saying that if
you bought it for the sake of shearing, you'd be obligated, we
don't mean in this extreme case that he automatically reverts to him
as soon as you're done shearing. It would mean until I'm done
shearing all of them, 30 days or 30 days is left up,
that basically means you're, if you purchased them, that you own them
until you're done with the shearing, then you would be obligated. But
אין הכי נמי, ein hachi nami, if they would revert back in
the middle of the shearing, after you're done with each one it
would revert back, then that's their area of debate. Okay, so here's
the question of when you sheared it you owned it, you owned
the sheep, but then you didn't own the sheep when you finished
all the shearings, are you still obligated or not? The גמרא Gemara's
leaves it as a debate. Now, moving on. הלוקח גז צאנו של
חבירו. halokeach gez tzono shel chaveiro. You're purchasing, if you purchase the
shearing of your friend's sheep, not of a non-Jew, right? So, so
Charlie here has his sheep laden with wool, I buy the wool
off... off of the sheep, meaning they're still on the sheep, but
I buy them while they're attached, the wool. And then I shear
it. Okay, so that's the case here in the משנה. It's not
a non-Jew, okay, but it's not my sheep. So what does the
משנה say? By the way, you realize that the גמרא Gemara put
all the משניות Mishnayot of this פרק perek into one משנה. Which
is why so so
oh, I'm sorry, it's really an off day for me. I'm excuse
me. I don't think I had maybe I just need to have
my cup of coffee this morning. Anyway, so it's not that case.
That was the non-Jew case. This was the case of excuse me,
this was the case of just that you are purchasing we it's
already being sold. Charlie sheared his sheep. They're it's already in the
marketplace. It's being sold. I purchase it from Charlie. Charlie has yet
to give his gift to the כהן. Kohen. So there it says
that if any amount is left in Charlie's possession, he uses that
to give to the כהן. Kohen. If he sells all of it
to me, then I have the responsibility to give it to the
כהן. Kohen. That's the case. So let's take a look. הלוקח גז
צאנו של חברו. Halokeach gez tzono shel chavero. מאן תנא דהיכא דאיכא
שיורא גבי מוכר בתר מוכר אזלינן? Man tanna deheicha de'ika shiyura gabei
mocher batar mocher azlinan? Who is the תנא Tanna that says that
if there's a little bit left over to the seller, then it's
the seller's obligation? So אמר רב חסדא רב יהודה היא. Amar Rav
Chisda Rav Yehuda hi. It's רב יהודה. Rav Yehuda. דתנן, Detnan, we
taught in the משנה by פאה, Pe'ah, המוכר קלחי אילן בתוך שדהו.
Hamocher kilchei ilan betoch sadehu. If you are selling like a clump
of trees in your field. You basically have a grain field and
there are some random trees growing, okay, and you're selling individual trees
in that field. So you give the person gives פאה Pe'ah on
the trees that he that he buys. נותן פאה לכל אחד ואחד.
Noten Pe'ah lechol echad ve'echad. So the person you the person so
so the person who purchased the trees has to give פאה Pe'ah
for each individual tree. אמר רב יהודה, Amar Rav Yehuda, רב יהודה
Rav Yehuda says אימתי, Eimatai, when is that true? בזמן שלא שייר
בעל השדה. Bizman shelo shiyer ba'al hasadeh. If the owner of the
field did not leave any trees over for himself. אבל שייר בעל
השדה, Aval shiyer ba'al hasadeh, if I left a tree over for
myself and I sold you let's say four of the trees and
I kept one that are growing here, then נותן פאה על הכל.
Noten Pe'ah al hakol. Then I have to give, I still give
the פאה Pe'ah and I give it for all of the trees.
So it's similar type of an idea. You see the analogy. I
sold it to you before I did my obligation. I do the
whole obligation if I still have something left over. That was the
גמרא's Gemara initial attempt. So the גמרא Gemara says one minute. אמר
ליה רבא, Amar lei Rava, so רבא Rava said back, והא מר
הוא דאמר, Veha mar hu de'amar, one minute, you yourself say when
you explain that case, והוא שהתחיל בעל השדה לקצור, Vehu shehitchil ba'al
hasadeh liktzor, that that's only if the obligation already fell upon me.
When would the obligation fall upon me? If I started to harvest.
So if I started to harvest, okay, then it's when I'm obligated
to leave פאה. Pe'ah. And then once the obligation fell on me
and I had all of the trees, then I sold you some,
I still retain my original obligation. You got the scenario? I started
harvesting, I had all the trees, I'm obligated, then I sell you
some, then if I retain at least one tree, then I have
to give everything. That's when the obligation already fell upon me. וכי
תימא הכא נמי והוא שהתחיל לגזוז, Vechi teima hacha nami vehu shehitchil
ligzoz, maybe here too it's the same. I really am confused this
morning. So here because again, I was, you know, last time I
thought I was mistaken, I was I realized I was wrong. So
anyway, when I when I revised the case about buying from Charlie,
it was actually it was the way I'd said it originally. I
didn't just buy from Charlie the sheared wool, I bought from Charlie
the wool on his sheep, okay? So that's the scenario. Charlie is
selling me, I was right the first time, Charlie is selling me
the wool on his sheep. If he sells me all the wool
on his sheep, then when I shear the wool, I have to
give. If he sells me ninety percent, then the little bit that's
left, I the stuff I shear I don't give, the stuff he
shears he does give. So the גמרא Gemara says one minute though.
The case by פאה Pe'ah where it remains by the original person
was when he already did the act that obligated him. In this
case where Charlie is selling me the wool on his sheep, Charlie
has yet to begin shearing. And if he doesn't begin shearing yet,
he only becomes obligated when he begins to shear. So in that
type of a case, why should why should it be all his
obligation if we if he sold it to me and then I
began shearing and Charlie had not yet begun shearing? וכי תימא הכא
נמי והוא שהתחיל לגזוז, Vechi teima hacha nami vehu shehitchil ligzoz, unless
you say here too it's the same scenario where Charlie began shearing
and therefore he had the obligation. So one minute.
בשלמא התם ובקצרכם את קציר
ארצכם כתיב, Bishlama hatam uvekutzrechem et katzir artzechem ketiv, it says when
you harvest, מעידנא דאתחיל לקצור
מחייב בכולה. Me'idna de'atchil liktzor mechayev bekula. As soon as you begin
harvesting, you have to give פאה Pe'ah on everything. That's when your
obligation begins. אלא הכא, Ela hacha, here by the shearing, מעידנא דאתחיל
למיגז לא מחייב
בכולה עדרא. Me'idna de'atchil lemigaz lo mechayev bekula adra. You're not obligated
when you begin shearing, right? Here what does the תורה say? גז
צאנך. Gez tzonecha. It doesn't say when you shear. It says you
give it on your shearings. So the obligation is only when you're
done. So here we've got the problem. Charlie sold me not the
shorn wool, like I said like I said but what I said
the first time, Charlie sold me the wool on the sheep itself.
If he sells me ninety-eight percent, then he has to give from
his remaining two percent. But the גמרא says why? When he sold
it to me he wasn't obligated yet. You're not obligated even if
you began shearing. You're not obligated until you actually have shorn it.
So since he wasn't yet obligated, why is it his obligation and
not mine? So the גמרא says אלא אמר
רבא. Ela amar Rava. So rather רבא Rava said, האי תנא הוא,
hai tanna hu, it's the following תנא, tanna, דתנן, detnan, אמר לו
amar lo מכור לי בני מעיה של פרה
זו, mechor li benei me'ah shel parah zo, sell me the, this
is our case of the מתנות matnot from the last פרק. perek.
Sell me, you know, the זרוע לחיים וקיבה, zero'a lechayayim ve-keivah, so
or sell me all of the intestines, והיה
בהם מתנות, ve-haya bahem matnot, and in it was the stomach, נותן
לכהן ואינו מנכה לו מן הדמים. noten lakohen ve-eino menakkeh lo min
ha-damim. Then I bought it, I have to give it to the
כהן, kohen, I can't get my money back because I should have
known that the stomach would be included. לקח ממנו במשקל, lakach mimenu
be-mishkal, if I bought it by weight, נותן לכהן ומנכה לו מן
הדמים, noten lakohen u-menakkeh lo min ha-damim, then I give it to
the כהן kohen and I can get my money back from the
butcher because he charged me for it. אלמא, alma, now here's the
point, why can I get my money back from the butcher? Because
from that we see in that last case, מתנות דכהן לא מזבין
איניש, matnot de-kohen lo mizabin inish, that although the butcher weighed it
and he sold it to me, basically I can say I never
wanted to buy this from you, right? Because it's not, I don't
have a right, it's not mine, and we'll also say that the
butcher never really wanted to sell it to me. Okay, so we're
going to interpret it as it was an accidental sale, I didn't
want to buy it, he didn't want to sell it, so therefore
I can get my money back from it. I give it to
the כהן, kohen, I get my money back. That's how we're going
to interpret that case. If that's true, הכא נמי, hacha nami, מתנות
דכהן לא מזבין איניש, matnot de-kohen lo mizabin inish, when Charlie sells
me for 98% of the wool that's on his sheep, so even
though he's not yet obligated, we're going to interpret the sale that
he never wanted to sell me the part of the wool from
which he would give the מתנות כהונה. matnot kehunah. Okay, that's how
we're going to, he wants to actually give it. He wants to
keep that part that's the מתנות כהונה matnot kehunah is going to
come from in his part. We're going to very generously interpret Charlie's
intentions and my intentions. I don't want to buy it, but obviously
I don't want to buy it, I don't want to have to
give, but we're also going to be very generously interpret that Charlie's
a good guy, so the same way by the butcher we're going
to say I can get my money back, he never would have
wanted to sell it. Here too we're going to say not that
Charlie's obligated and therefore already, he's not yet obligated, but we're just
going to choose to interpret that he never wanted to sell that.
Let me just finish. הלכך שייר מוכר, hilkach shiyer mocher, therefore if
there's even 1% left by Charlie, מוכר חייב, mocher chayav, then the
מוכר mocher gives,
דאמר ליה לוקח מתנה דכהן גבך היא, de-amar lei lokeh matna de-kohen
gabakh hi, hey Charlie, I never wanted to buy the מתנות כהונה
matnot kehunah off of you, so if you were selling me 99%,
I was intending that the מתנות כהונה matnot kehunah were going to
come from your remaining 1%. Okay. לא שייר לוקח חייב, lo shiyer
lokeh chayav, if I didn't leave anything by Charlie, then I'm obligated.
דאמר ליה מוכר מתנה דכהן לא זבני לך, de-amar lei mocher matna
de-kohen lo zabni lach, because then the מוכר mocher says, מתנה דכהן
לא זבני לך, matna de-kohen lo zabni lach, I did not sell
to you. Wait, דאמר ליה מוכר מתנה דכהן לא זבני
לך, de-amar lei mocher matna de-kohen lo zabni lach, I did not
sell to you, what? I should have sold to you?
I did, I didn't mean to sell
the מתנות, matnot, I don't know, hold on.
Alright, anyway, I'm not exactly getting the, but anyway, essentially in that
case, in that, wait
a minute, רבי הושעיא's Rabbi Hoshaya got a variation,
אם פירש
כל אני מוכר לך אין כאן לכהן כלום על זה.
im pirash kol ani mocher lach ein kan
lakohen kelum al zeh. Wait a minute,
oh yeah, here's the problem. The problem is that, ah I get
it, then it becomes like the case of the butcher. The case
of the butcher, even when he sells it to him, right, that's
what, in the case of the butcher even when he sells it
to him, he gives him the stomach, we say he didn't intend
to sell him the stomach, right? And therefore the stomach still goes
to the כהן kohen and I get my money back. So if
Charlie sells me 100%, right, then what we really say is again,
we interpret that Charlie never really would have wanted to sell me
the part to the כהן. kohen. Since he never really wanted to
sell it to me, it still remained Charlie's and therefore it still
goes to the כהן kohen because it really never transferred to me.
So then in theory maybe I could get a refund similar to
the case by the butcher. So the לא זבני לך lo zabni
lach is, it means the same thing like when the butcher weighed
it out. Yes, it changed hands, but we're going to choose to
interpret that he never wanted to sell. So the upshot of the
משנה is that although Charlie never had the חיוב chiyyuv yet, we're
going to choose to interpret that he's a good guy and I
certainly don't want to have to take on his obligations. So he
never sold it to me. If a little bit is left, it's
his. Even if everything transferred, he didn't really sell that part, that
was a mistake, it really remains Charlie's, so that part goes to
the כהן kohen because it really never left Charlie's possession. Okay, we
will end here.